It is
a privilege to be a detective.
Mark Birch: You deal with lots
and lots of horrible things,
that comes with the territory.
The majority of us
don't have to see these things,
don't have to
deal with these things.
The launch of the fifth
murder enquiry in such
a short space of time ...
Martin Brunning: Justice for
the victims is absolutely
the most important thing.
- You've been arrested
on suspicion of attempted
murder and murder.
- Could be worse.
Officer PTC: We can
only imagine the grief of
the families who lost
their loved ones in such
brutal circumstances.
- ... with your DNA.
How can that be?
- No comment.
Journalist PTC: The judge
said the murder showed a degree
of premeditation and planning.
He'd been stabbed and beaten.
Howard Groves: It was very
much a manhunt at that stage
of the investigation.
He knew that the
walls were closing in on him.
Stewart Gull: I always remember
a more experienced officer
telling me, you know, you,
you never forget these jobs,
and he was right.
VO: These are the detectives
who solved some of Britain's
most notorious homicides.
Now they re-live those cases.
Martin Brunning: Every fear
that I had was being realised
in front of my eyes.
VO: Through every twist and
turn of the investigation ...
Mark Birch: The only
way you forget about it is ...
is when you're asleep.
VO: Their personal accounts
reveal what it really takes
to capture a killer
and bring them to justice.
Howard Groves:
As a detective, you know, there,
there can't be any
greater honour than for you
to investigate the death- or
murder- of another human being.
Mark PTC: Fairly early
in my career I wanted
to be a detective.
I had thirty-one years in
the Police and I became Head
of CID for a police force.
You're entrusted with some
really, really serious stuff.
You're trusted by the
public to do the right thing.
Mark: This
was one of the most challenging,
one of the most difficult
enquiries I've had to deal with.
The level of violence that
was used was beyond anything
I'd ever dealt with before,
so I'll never forget it.
Mark PTC: It started
with a phone call from
the crime manager at the local
police station at Peterborough.
This guy Andrew Scanlan
had been reported missing
by his girlfriend
Louise earlier in November,
and it had been handled as
a Missing From Home enquiry
since then by a locum officer.
VO: When that phone call comes
through to DCS Mark Birch:,
Andrew's been missing
for five weeks.
Unemployed and engaging
in low-level crime,
he was estranged from his
family and living on Dickens
Street with his girlfriend,
Louise, when he disappeared .
At first, there was
no particular cause for concern.
Mark PTC: Louise had received
a text message saying 'no need
to worry, I'm off to London',
or words to that effect.
Given that Andrew Scanlan was an
adult, thirty-five years of age,
adults are allowed
to go missing.
Nothing was specifically leaping
out at that stage to say
that we've got a big problem
here, or there is a problem,
other than trying to find out
and unearth where he was
and if he was safe and well.
VO: But as police
continue making routine checks,
they discover a lead.
During the five weeks
Andrew's been gone,
his bank
card is in regular use.
Not in London, as his
text to his girlfriend suggests,
but much closer to home.
Mark PTC: It was being
accessed every Friday
and a hundred and ninety
pounds was being withdrawn.
So the Missing From Home
officer set up observations on
the cashpoint where this hundred
and ninety pounds was being
withdrawn in Peterborough.
Mark PTC: You've got a card
and a bank that suddenly money's
being withdrawn from,
but it's not being withdrawn
by Andrew Scanlan.
There is something
going on here.
VO: Under Mark Birch:'s lead,
what had been a routine Missing
Person's enquiry now becomes
a criminal investigation
of the most serious kind.
Mark PTC: Ultimately
I'm responsible for homicides
in the, in the county.
People talk about gut instinct.
The truth of the matter is,
when you look at gut instinct
it isn't gut instinct, is it?
It's based around
your own personal experience,
it's based around the facts
that are put in front
of you and you make a,
a decision.
Having sat down, talked through
all the facts that surrounded
the case, they were all giving
me a feeling that something
had happened to Andrew Scanlan.
VO: Mark Birch: suspects the
very worst - that Andrew is
not missing, but murdered.
With no clear evidence beyond
a misused bank card he has
to make a quick
and difficult decision.
Mark PTC: We're now talking
three days before Christmas,
police officers
are the same as everyone else,
they've got
families, they've got a life,
they've got things
that are going on.
These are the sort of things
that were going through my head.
Mark PTC: Don't get me wrong
- it wouldn't matter what time
of year, what time if day,
if we're talking investigation
of a murder
it's going to happen.
But what you don't want to
do is put the balloon up
and start a murder
enquiry using a substantial
amount of staff
when you didn't need to.
Especially if it wasn't
a murder enquiry in the end,
if Andrew Scanlan happened
to be living in a flat
in London safe and well.
Mark PTC: Every
day matters in a murder enquiry.
Better to make a decision
that's wrong than not make
a decision at all.
There's no doubt in my mind that
this guy has been murdered and
if we don't pick it up now we're
going to lose more evidence.
VO: With his decision
made, DCS Birch escalates
the investigation and builds a
team to work through Christmas.
Mark PTC: We've got five
or six weeks of evidence that
potentially could have gone.
And that includes CCTV footage.
You know, some,
some cameras they only roll
on a 24-hour clock.
There's the forensic evidence.
Wherever the scene
was, where he was taken from,
where he's been killed,
where he's been deposited,
there's evidence
there that could be lost.
There's witnesses' evidence.
So a witness may remember
something after a day or two.
Give them five or six
weeks, it becomes less clear.
For me it's now about retrieving
all the evidence I possibly can.
Mark PTC: I'm going to
ramp up the number of officers
Involved in the investigation.
I'm going to ramp up
the techniques that we use
in terms of bringing
in a murder enquiry room,
which is going
to involve lots of staff,
lots of
time and lots of money.
VO: The first,
and most obvious suspect,
is the man who'd been
using Andrew's bank card-
Peter Cottrell.
He's now brought in for
questioning and turns out
to be Andrew's best friend.
Peter had no bank account
of his own so Andrew lent
him his card to
pay in and withdraw his wages.
Mark PTC: The fact that
the bank account was being
used actually
became a bit of a red herring.
Sometimes you can put a
load of effort into something
and you can work your
socks off, and you'll get to
a place and it's,
it's gone the wrong direction,
that's not the answer.
Now turn away, forget about
it, move on to the next place.
VO: Andrew's girlfriend
Louise is also questioned.
Together, she and Peter
produce a compelling new lead.
On the night Andrew
was last seen, he had a visit.
Mark PTC: The version
of events that Peter and Louise
gave us was simply this: so on
the seventeenth of November two
thousand and six they
get a knock on the door
and Mark Baigent is at the door.
James Baigent
was sitting in the car outside.
VO: Mark and James Baigent
are Andrew Scanlan's younger
half-brothers.
The three share the same mother,
Linda, who has recently died.
Mark PTC: Mark
Baigent comes into the address,
tells Andrew that as a result
of their mother's death
he's been left a sum of money,
about five thousand pounds,
but that Andrew Scanlan needed
to come with Mark and
James Baigent and travel
down to Dorset where the lawyer
was going to
give Andrew Scanlan this money.
And of course,
for Andrew Scanlan,
a sum of money of
five thousand pounds is
a massive amount of money.
VO: If the story is
true then the Baigents,
Andrew's half-brothers, are
likely to be the last people
to have seen him alive.
VO: Detective
Superintendent Mark Birch:
has new suspects in his hunt
for missing
35-year-old Andrew Scanlan.
Andrew's half-brothers Mark
and James Baigent were seen
picking him up from
his home in Peterborough on
the night he disappeared.
VO: Using number
plate recognition technology,
Mark and his team
are able to follow their path.
Mark PTC:
We had tracked the car.
What route did the car take?
And we knew Andrew had his
phone with him so we could
also overlap that
intelligence with
the intelligence from the car.
We knew that there'd
been some text messages
and some Voicemails sent...
and what was clearly obvious
is that the car,
instead of going into central
London as one of the text messages actually said-
what it had actually
done is travelled round
the M25 and then had
left the M25, heading towards,
and near by
the address of, James Baigent.
VO: The route tracked by
the police stops well short
of Dorset, where the brothers had told Andrew he'd be
collecting a legacy
from their late mother.
Nor does it take him
to London, dropped off by mates,
as suggested
in the text message.
Mark PTC: You can make
a supposition: did they forcibly
make him send that text
message and to try and put
his girlfriend off the scent?
But more importantly I think
they did it to try and put
the police off the scent.
VO: Instead police
tracked the car to Aldershot,
32 miles south-west of London.
Meanwhile, DCS Birch
and his team are exploring
why Andrew's brothers
may want to cause him harm.
They believe there's
a clue in the date he was taken.
Mark PTC: This
was the seventeenth of November.
Their mother died
on the eighteenth of October,
so one-month's
anniversary of her death.
VO: According to Andrew
Scanlan's girlfriend Louise,
the relationship between Andrew
and his brothers is fractured.
Mark PTC: Just shortly
after the death of their mother,
Mark Baigent had turned up at
the Dickens Road address and by
all accounts Mark Baigent
and Andrew Scanlan had a fight.
Mark Baigent was telling
Andrew Scanlan not to come
to their mother's funeral.
And there was a massive
amount of antagonism
and hatred between James and
Mark Baigent and Andrew Scanlan.
And that was based around
the fact that they believed
that Andrew Scanlan was
directly responsible for
their mother's death.
Mark PTC: And the reason
they blamed him for
their mother's death
was Andrew was a drug addict,
he'd had various other
problems and she'd been there
to support Andrew.
And they felt that had
put an undue level of stress
upon her and had
led to her early death.
VO: The police investigation
soon reveals more bad blood
between the brothers.
Ten years earlier Mark Baigent
had been given a four-year
prison term for attempted
armed robbery and possession
of a firearm.
Mark PTC: There was a huge
suspicion amongst the brothers
that Andrew had been responsible
for informing the police about
an armed
robbery some years earlier.
So this hatred was all
the time being ramped up
so that as soon as
the mother was dead,
now they had no reason
for him to stay alive.
They hated him.
From that very moment
they were hatching a plan.
VO: Mark Birch: now has
a motive and a theory - that the
Baigents marked the one-month
anniversary of their mother's
death in the most brutal
way possible: abducting
and then killing
their hated half-brother.
Mark PTC: From the moment
their mother died I think Andrew
Scanlan was a dead man walking.
VO: The Baigent brothers
were questioned early on in the
enquiry, when Andrew was still
presumed missing, not dead.
They claimed not
to have seen him.
If they have murdered their
half-brother there's no
clue yet as to how or where.
But slowly the evidence stacks
up to support Birch's theory.
Mark PTC: So we now knew
roughly the route that Andrew
Scanlan had travelled
when he left Dickens Street
in Peterborough and
ended up round into Hampshire.
Now Mark and James Baigent
actually had denied
having anything
to do with him at this stage.
In fact, James had said
they hadn't gone round there.
Suddenly we've got lies and
we had a motive in terms of
the hatred that was going on,
so at that stage it was becoming
increasingly obvious to me that
he was going to be dead ...
and we were looking for a body.
The problem was we just
didn't know where the body was.
VO: As the police dig deeper
it becomes evident that Mark
and James Baigent
did not act alone.
Mark PTC: I then start
analysing all the telephones
that we've
got, and what became obvious,
there was a third
male Involved in this case.
And this
was a close friend of theirs,
a guy by
the name of Jeff Woods.
Jeff was a
tree surgeon by trade,
he had a van
with all the cutting material,
and he lived not too far away
from where James Baigent lived.
VO: Woods and the Baigent
brothers have known each
other for years.
Mark PTC: All three of
them are Involved in war games,
they liked to go out
and dress up as soldiers
and all this sort of stuff.
But they were really tight
as a group and got
on very well together.
And it suddenly became fairly
obvious that the three of
them were likely to have been
Involved in Andrew Scanlan's
disappearance
and ultimately death.
VO: Now the police have three
prime suspects: brothers
Mark and James Baigent
and their friend Jeff Woods.
Mark PTC: So the next
plan for me is arrest.
But it isn't just
a case of 'Right, that's it,
we're just going to go and
arrest' because I don't have
to arrest this second,
and what I wanted to do was
plan the arrest
so that all three of them
were arrested simultaneously.
VO: DCS Birch wants
to catch the men off-guard.
Mark PTC: We've got a group
of officers at each location to
carry out those arrests.
We've also got forensic staff
and we want to retrieve as much
trace evidence
from those scenes as possible.
We were looking to find trace
evidence of Andrew Scanlan's
body, or existence.
VO: The police make their
move in the early hours
of the morning.
Mark Baigent, James Baigent
and Jeff Woods are arrested
on suspicion of murder.
As the men are taken
out the forensic teams move in.
Mark PTC: What became really quite apparent,
that all three of them had
researched heavily now to not
get caught on forensic evidence.
And we knew that by the
literature and the DVD's we'd
found at the addresses.
From NCIS,
CSI, American programmes.
We had a witness statement
that identified that they were
seen cleaning
the Ford Escort that they
travelled round the M25
in with Andrew Scanlan.
And by cleaning it, they'd not
only cleaned it out properly,
but they'd wrapped sticky tape
round their hands and they'd
taped down the back seats
and they'd taped down
the interior of the car.
So they wanted to get rid
of any idea that he'd ever
been in that car,
either alive or dead.
They'd planned this, in
their minds, quite meticulously.
They actually thought they were
going to get away with murder.
VO: The suspects are held
at Thorpe Wood Police Station
in Peterborough.
DCS Birch has ninety-six hours
to charge them or release them.
Mark PTC: The clock has
started and now we need to
start getting
on with the interviews.
We can put different
things that are being said
by each individual
to the other individuals.
It's quite a complex
strategized process.
VO: The three
men are questioned separately.
Mark PTC: They were
arrogant, they were confident,
they were nasty.
VO: And at first the
detectives make little headway.
Mark PTC: All three
of them just refused to give
us any explanation.
They were simply
brothers-in-arms.
They were not going to tell
the police anything
and I think all three of them
thought 'we stick to this story,
we're going to be home dry'.
VO: As the interviews
continue in Peterborough,
house-to-house enquiries in
Hampshire start to bear fruit.
Mark PTC: We start to unearth
these bits of information
to put to them even further.
So for example, witnesses
had seen people trying
to clean the Escort.
Whilst they were doing that,
seen nearby was a
tree surgeon's van.
And of course we know that
Jeff Woods was a tree surgeon.
VO: The witness statements
provide Mark Birch:
with vital ammunition
in the interview suites.
Mark PTC:
So when you're questioning,
what you're doing with each
question as you move forwards
is revealing what you know.
We would have gone back
time and time and time again.
It was hours
and hours of interviews.
VO: So far, all three men have
repeatedly refused to discuss
the murder with detectives.
But now, after two full days of
interview, one of them cracks.
Mark PTC: Suddenly out
of nowhere Jeff Woods decided
he wanted to talk to us.
VO: Thirty-five-year-old Andrew Scanlan has been missing,
believed murdered,
for nearly two months.
The police have
three suspects under arrest,
two of them
Andrew's half-brothers.
All claim their innocence.
With forty-eight hours to go
before they must be released
one of them, tree surgeon
Jeff Woods, agrees to talk.
Mark PTC: He doesn't have
to be the Brain of Britain
to work out as we're moving
on through our questioning
over hours and hours and
hours that we know an awful lot.
And that actually,
as it stands at the moment,
he's going to be charged with
the murder of Andrew Scanlan.
And he had to think of a story
to get himself out of the frame.
VO: Out of the blue,
Jeff Woods tells investigators
he knows the whereabouts
of Andrew Scanlan's body.
Mark PTC: Did it,
did it surprise us?
Yes, it did, because suddenly
out of nowhere - at quite
a late stage in
our custody time-limit as well.
That's another
thing that, you know,
you need to understand
that we were getting towards
the end of the time
when we either had to charge
or we had to release
them without charge.
But it's not uncommon
once you do get a,
a complicity
of individuals engaged in a,
in something of this nature,
for one of them to try
and protect themselves
and say they didn't do it.
What Jeff was telling
us, in real simple terms,
was that he
didn't commit the murder.
All he did was assist
in getting rid of the body.
That the two guys,
the Baigent brothers,
had killed Andrew Scanlan
and then on top of that he
was quite prepared to
take us and show us where
the body had
been deposited.
- We're at Sandy Hill
Road and we're about to do
a route walk with Jeff Woods.
- OK, do you want to lead on?
VO: Jeff has brought police
to the outskirts of Aldershot,
one hundred and
twenty miles from Peterborough.
Mark PTC: Just in the end
it was literally booked him
out of custody and took
him to the location where he,
where he wanted to go.
He starts to
talk to the officers.
We're video-recording it
so everything can be seen
as being completely
above board and legitimate.
[Jeff talking to
police officers]
Mark PTC: We were actually
coming towards the end of
our custody time limits.
We've only got a short period of
time that we've got to then go
out and find this body and then
do all the work that would need
to be done around that.
VO: If Jeff Woods knows
his custody deadline will
soon expire, this could
be a deliberate delaying tactic.
Mark PTC: Is
he telling us the truth?
You know, suddenly he's out of
nowhere he wants to talk this.
Is it a ruse to try and, er,
waste up a load of police time?
- Right, I need
to get my bearings now.
- Here, it's it's,
through here.
Mark PTC: He was kind
of 'Yeah, I think it's here,
I think it's there,
oh I'm not really sure it's
somewhere up here,
it's somewhere round here'.
'Cause if he was too sure
I think he was thinking
well it's 'cause
we've all planned it together,
the three of us planned this,
we always talked about
where we're going
to put the body.
We always talked about
where we're going to kill him.
Jeff: Officer: If you can see, um, that, that hut,
it might be
something like that hut inside.
And that's what
you're looking for.
A hut like that, um ...
It's a bunker-like
complex is it?
An old bunker?
Yes.
OK.
An old bunker and you go
behind this, this bunker.
I think I might
have come too far up,
I think it
might be further down this way.
VO: It begins to look
as if Jeff Woods may indeed
be leading police
on a wild-goose chase.
Jeff: No, it's
not further than that there.
So it's from here this way.
So it's in here somewhere.
Mark PTC: So we get to
the vicinity of where he says
the body may
or may not be.
We don't know whether he's,
it's some trick to put
us off the scent.
Officer Jeff: I know I'm here. I'm definitely,
definitely here.
It's on the end
of this path and it's in here.
OK, so when you walk in here
was there trees touching you
or anything like that?
Oh yeah, yeah...
There was trees touching you?
I did say, remember I said
thick pine trees in the middle.
Officer: Yes.
So it's here but I need
to just ... if I can step In
and have a look?
Yes.
I'm not going
to in, I won't go very far in.
[Jeff searching]
There's your hut, there.
Oh yeah.
There's you hut, bingo!
Hang on.
Hang on, hang on.
Mark PTC: As soon as he points
out an area we can't have him
trooping in there and trouncing
all over the area because all
you're doing is contaminating it
with one of your suspects'
DNA and trace evidence.
Officer Jeff: So in
relation to the hut,
we need to go round
the back of the hut.
Yeah.
Round the back.
And how far behind
it is it there?
Um... I, I'll
know by the floor.
Right, OK.
Well I think
I'll know by the floor.
Like it may
remind...I did it...
when I was here this was...
I couldn't, I couldn't
see you from here so ...
Yeah, from, from my point
of view what I want to try is
actually take into a different,
from a different angle.
So we know that, not the
angle you came in from before.
Well if we walk towards
it and then I go right round it.
What, what I was going to
suggest is there's a path down,
you know that path there that
skirts round the edge of here?
Yeah.
I'm wondering if we can
go down that path a little bit
and then look back
across first of all,
before we go ... clean route.
So basically
we just keep a clean route, OK?
No, no, no, I understand
what you're saying.
Yeah, that's fine,
I understand.
Mark PTC: We finally get
to a point where he points
out 'That's where he is,
that's where I think it is'.
OK, just step, step back again.
That's it.
It's either
that one, or that one there.
There are two ...
That area there?
Or the one in front.
It's either one of those or...
That one or there?
Yes.
Mark PTC: So of course, the
minute he points it out we've
then got to go in with
a forensic team and recover
that scene, or search
that scene as best we can.
VO: While Jeff Woods is
returned to custody the forensic
specialists move in.
Mark PTC: So a forensic
team went into the clearing.
There was an
outbuilding that was nearby,
it looked like
a bunker of some sort.
And then just to the
right there was a shallow grave,
just a slight
indentation shallow grave.
Mark PTC: What actually
transpired was it was
two shallow graves.
And you had the torso,
the main part of the body
in one part
of the shallow grave.
Literally a matter of a couple
of feet away was the severed
head and hands of Andrew
Scanlan in a separate grave.
VO: The body
of missing 35-year-old Andrew
Scanlan has been discovered
- dismembered and lying in two
shallow graves
on the outskirts of Aldershot.
For DCS Birch,
dreadful as the discovery is,
there's some comfort in knowing
Andrew has been found at last.
Mark PTC: There's a feeling
of achieving what you set
out to achieve.
I felt really proud
of my team, I felt really proud
of the investigation.
I can't say I took any
like huge elation out of it
'cause it's not
like that for me.
It was a professional outcome.
I felt really sorry for the
guy who died, Andrew Scanlan.
Mark PTC: It's all
about recovering
the body with dignity.
That's, you know,
that's a really big issue,
believe it or not.
But recovering every
evidential opportunity
you can get 'cause you'll
get one bite at this.
Once you've done that,
if you've lost anything
in the recovery stage, you're
never going to have another go.
Mark PTC: Just recovering
the body will take hours
and hours and hours
and hours - days actually.
Sometimes you won't remove a
body in a circumstance
like that for
twenty-four, thirty-six hours.
VO: One puzzle for Mark Birch:
and his team is why Andrew's
killers have
buried his body as they have.
Mark PTC: If you were going
to sever the head and the hands
because you were thinking
about maybe dental records
and fingerprint removal, well
you wouldn't put them in a
grave immediately adjacent
to where you put the body.
And my assumption is that I
think that they buried him in
a shallow grave in the dark -
and it is pitch-dark -
and then probably gone
back a day or two later
and there's probably
something sticking out
of the ground when
rigamortis maybe has
set in,
or something has happened.
It looks as though that
the decapitation and the hand
removal was simply to
cover the body up and bury
the body better.
News presenter: The body
was found near a site where
the three accused
men played war games together.
The Baigent brothers came
here, to Andrew Scanlan's house,
and enticed him into their car
by claiming they all needed
to go to Dorset to sort
out their late mother's Will.
Instead, it's said, they
drove him to Hampshire where
he was beaten
and stabbed to death.
VO: Now Andrew's
body has been found,
DCS Birch hopes it will
offer up the evidence he needs
to charge all
three men with his murder.
VO: The post-mortem
will be critical.
Mark PTC: The forensic
pathologists in our country
are absolutely brilliant.
It's not unusual to take
ten, twelve hours to carry
out a forensic post-mortem.
You know, the post-mortem
examination is absolutely
carried out with
infinite detail.
VO: Andrew's bruised
and dismembered body reveals
the extent of the violence
inflicted on him by his killers.
Mark PTC: The injuries that
he had were two stab wounds
to his body,
and they didn't kill him.
He's got bruising all over
his body consistent with
being beaten
with a baseball bat.
He's been
tortured pretty much.
Mark PTC: You know they've,
they've given him a
real good hiding.
And then
they strangled him.
Mark PTC: Dragged his
body up the hill,
dragged him into the woods,
dug a shallow grave
and buried him
in a shallow grave.
But there was no definitive
cause of death in this case.
They wanted to make
him hurt before they killed him.
Mark PTC: The level of violence
was beyond anything I'd ever
dealt with before.
The, the sheer hatred and
the sheer vehement wish to, to,
to kill him and to put him
in pain and be rid of him
shone through all the way.
If you think what Andrew
Scanlan must have been going
through for that last
fifteen minutes to half an hour,
he must
have been absolutely terrified.
VO: DCS Birch still needs
forensic proof that the Baigent
brothers and Jeff Woods
are together responsible
for Andrew's murder.
After hours of painstaking work
the pathologist delivers it.
Mark PTC: We found a small
shard in the spine of Andrew
Scanlan that potentially matched
a piece of metal, or an axe,
that was found at James
Baigent's house and the paint
that was on there
was a potential match.
We found fibres in the car
that were belonging to Andrew
Scanlan so we could positively
not only put him into the car
by witness evidence
but also by trace evidence.
Mark PTC: There was a pair
of shoes found at Jeff Woods's
address that upon
examination had traces
of Andrew Scanlan's blood.
And there were also fibres
found on other items of clothing
that would match between the
individuals and Andrew Scanlan.
Mark PTC: We had
Jeff Woods telling us the story,
we had the body found where
he said the body was found.
All wrapped up together
you've got a really strong
prosecution case.
And that's
without witness testimony.
VO: What witness statements
do soon reveal is
the wider Involvement
of the Baigent family.
Mark PTC: We
had the wife of James Baigent,
Charlotte Baigent,
telling people at a party,
a group of individuals,
that they'd been Involved
in the murder of Andrew Scanlan.
In fact she went
a lot further, she,
the version she was telling
was that they'd done a
lot more hideous things to the
body than actually had occurred.
She was basically saying, you
know ... my family are murderers
and if you're not careful
they're going to murder you.
She assisted them in
the clean-up exercise,
she got rid of their
clothing, she got rid of,
um, evidence in the case
and she tried to lead us astray.
So witness testimony
also became really significant
in this case.
VO: DCS Mark Birch: now
has enough evidence to send
his three suspects to trial.
Mark PTC: All three of the
men were charged with murder,
remanded into custody,
and then some months later
we got a trial with
the three of them for murder.
VO: As the trial starts
the relationship between
the accused changes rapidly.
Once a band of brothers, now
they're turning on each other.
Mark PTC: There is a term
called a 'cut-throat defence'.
It became a situation where
these three guys who'd been
tight as anything,
who'd been really close,
suddenly you had Jeff
saying, 'You two killed him,
all I did was help.
I didn't kill him, I had
nothing to do with the murder'.
And then on the counter-argument
was that you had
the two brothers saying,
'Well this didn't happen,
we were just going to give
him a beating because we didn't
like him, Jeff you killed him'.
VO: The trial runs for seven
weeks at Cambridge Crown Court
before the jury reaches
its verdict in February 2008.
Mark PTC: The verdict was
a unanimous decision by
the jury who
didn't believe any of it.
Thought all three of the men
were complicit in the murder
of Andrew Scanlan and found
all three men guilty of murder.
In sentencing, the judge
said the murder showed
a degree of
pre-meditation and planning.
Andrew Scanlan was kidnapped,
humiliated in the minutes
before he died, his body
dismembered and then concealed.
All three men
were jailed for life.
Journalist PTC: James Baigent,
who the judge said was
the plot's ringleader,
will spend a minimum of
twenty-four years in prison.
His brother Mark
a minimum of twenty-two years,
and Jeff Woods who assisted in
the murder and the dismemberment
a minimum of twenty years.
The judge said he had no
doubt the two brothers had
used episodes of CSI
to try and cover their tracks
and he praised the real
police and forensic service
for bringing the three
of them to justice.
VO: Charlotte Baigent
is convicted of assisting her
husband and brother-in-law
and sentenced to twelve months.
Mark PTC: I was there for
the verdict and the sentencing.
I felt really proud of my
team, I felt really proud of
the investigation, I felt really, really proud
of everyone's
Involvement in this case.
I think the sibling hatred,
that was the thing that was
really something I'd
never come across to that extent
and you kind of think
that siblings shouldn't behave
like that to one another.
And so that was the thing that
really stuck in my mind about
this, this murder
and, and how they behaved.
It was that sheer callousness,
that sheer cold-bloodedness
towards their
own flesh and blood.
Mark PTC: They could have just
disassociated themselves
and gone off and li ... lived
a happy life but something
inside them gee'd them up that
they had to do it for their
own egotistical reasons.
VO: Peter Cottrell,
Andrew's friend,
was there on the night
Andrew was taken away by his
half-brothers, supposedly
to claim his inheritance.
Peter Cottrell PTC: No way I,
at that point when his brothers
turned up that I thought it,
they were going to do what
they did to him.
It, it makes me sick to
the stomach thinking about that.
It's just so, so dark.
It's such a dark crime.
Peter PTC: The fact that
they were related to Andrew
is absolutely shocking because
Andrew wouldn't hurt anybody.
He, he wasn't that way.
I never seen him
fall out with anyone.
All, all I saw was kindness
and, and happiness with Andrew,
that's, that's who he was.
Never an angry person,
always happy-go-lucky.
I wish he was still here.
VO: Today Andrew
Scanlan's resting place
is an unmarked grave.
Mark PTC: It's human life,
as simple as that, you know.
We've got the right to life
and ultimately no one has
got the right
to take that life away from you.
Andrew Scanlan might not have
been an upstanding member
of the public,
he might have been a low-level
criminal and he was
estranged from his family,
and whatever he was
he didn't deserve to be
a victim of murder.
He didn't deserve
what happened to him.